[SPEAKER_01]: I have been listening probably most of your talks, so I tried to come with a topic that maybe was not discussed directly, and maybe it would be interesting to go deeper into it.
[SPEAKER_01]: There are obviously quite a spread view about the idea of nibbāna as being something positive, almost a kind of
[SPEAKER_01]: heaven or a state, place to go.
[SPEAKER_01]: They even say, you know, oh, let's practice together, so we go together to nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes they don't say in such an extreme way, but definitely we can see the ideas and views have a kind of elements of that kind of permanent space or permanent state where you go.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, of course, there is also becoming some kind of position.
[SPEAKER_01]: Kind of saying no nibbāna is a negative thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the tribe probably taken against some kind of facts and arguments to fight against the the thinkers of positive nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what you can say about that one?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what do you do?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's positive?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's negative?
[SPEAKER_01]: They were not very clear.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, positive, we can start, you know, just what is nibbāna?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it really a state to go?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it anything positive about it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there are a lot of misconceptions around nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, since you don't have any specific misconceptions, informed questions, I'll just tell you the understanding of nibbāna, and then you'll see wherever it fits.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, absence of passion, absence of greed, aversion, delusion, as a mode of being, is what nibbāna is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, absence of possibility of passion, absence of possibility of aversion, absence of possibility of distraction and delusion, is what nibbāna is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's... you can take it to be positive, you can take it to be negative, take it whichever way you want, if you take it to be absence of these three things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's certainly not a mystical state.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's certainly not a state that happens to you, in a sense of, oh, I had this experience, must have been nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a state you develop by removing greed, aversion, delusion entirely from all layers of your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this nibbāna, why the body is still here?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why are we still alive?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then parinibbāna?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, if you understand nibbāna while the body is still here, alive, then you'll know what parinibbāna is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, talking about parinibbāna, when a person doesn't even have nibbāna, it's meaningless.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you know, right now, confirm or deny that there's some kind of state.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can still feel, like, sense of... there is still a sense of experience in nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Five hundred degrees.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what do you mean?
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot confirm or deny that it's a state?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, nibbāna wouldn't be some kind of after-death?
[SPEAKER_01]: This is still some kind of continuity, that you still experience something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, saying that there is continuity or that there isn't continuity is meaningless to the mind that doesn't even have the right view, let alone nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because any idea of saying what's after, implies after, which means it's already a form of continuity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you say there is nothing after, the fact that the person thinks they can think after is nothing, that's already something for them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a state in as much as your current mood is a state.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what do you think nibbāna is?
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know, because nibbāna...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't think so.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even the word says it's in a kind of state.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just means ending of something, like extinction, ending of bhāva, you know, something which you assumed as is, there, conceived.
[SPEAKER_01]: When one sees through it, you know, how can be there, let's say, still experience without
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how would that not be a state?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, if it's nibbāna, state is a bhāva... Say nibbāna is extinction of bhāva, it's extinction of being, it's still something as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: How can you even talk about it?
[SPEAKER_00]: How can you aim for it?
[SPEAKER_00]: How can you experience it if it's not a state?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, nibbāna can be never really in front of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a thing there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's more like, let's say, context.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, in that sense, no thing can be in front of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is your being, is your bhāva in front of you?
[SPEAKER_00]: Bhāva... Is bhāva something in front of you?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or is it your context?
[SPEAKER_01]: I would say that bhāva is more...
[SPEAKER_01]: Is your being something you can attend to?
[SPEAKER_01]: I would say yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're attending to it, that's not your being.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's on account of your being.
[SPEAKER_00]: Being... your being is already where your situation is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can attend on account of it, but you cannot attend it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you are it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I said...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like saying your I can attend to itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I thought, like, being, in a sense, in the front, like, is conceived, it's...
[SPEAKER_00]: Being is conceived, but the conceiving does not happen in front of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: The conceiving is not a matter
[SPEAKER_00]: So, conceiving is the direct result of lacking that understanding of that fundamental context.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, perceiving is already conceiving.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why I thought, like, not knowing, not recognizing that the context
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but you can already see that that's not quite adequate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because why would the being, just simply being there, regardless of the content,
[SPEAKER_00]: Why would that be the content of your context?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the whole point of being.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's non-specific, not bound to this or that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just the fact that you are means that's what being is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if nibbāna is extinction of that, that's what it means.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in that sense, even that being cannot be in front of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is nibbāna then?
[SPEAKER_00]: If being cannot be in front of you, what would then constitute extinguishing of that being?
[SPEAKER_01]: Five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, okay, but let's keep within this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll just provide an answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, five aggregates, so...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if being is always on the level of the context, your being here and now, what would be extinguishing with that?
[SPEAKER_00]: What would you extinguish?
[SPEAKER_00]: Does extinguishing of the context mean there is no context?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's impossible, then, for nibbāna to not be an experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: The experience is still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is why I said five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's, again, not go into five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stay with the being.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the being that cannot be in front of you, you extinguish the context of that being and that cannot be in front of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But is it correct, then, to say that that's not... that that's, like, not a special experience, or that... or that's a special experience, or that... oh, well, that cannot be, sort of, experienced in the same sense as bhāva is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It cannot be directly or indirectly experienced.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which one is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: How can there be extinguishing of your being, unless that's also your situation in the time?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, there's not anymore this kind of conceiving of me and the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you just experience as it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, nibbāna is experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nibbāna is experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what's the difference, then, between the experience of nibbāna and the experience of non-nibbāna?
[SPEAKER_01]: The one is more like an idea of nibbāna, more conceived, affected by illusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry, non-nibbāna is more of an idea of nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Non-nibbāna?
[SPEAKER_00]: Nibbāna is more of an idea of nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: What does it mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry, I've lost it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if the... Again, let's...
[SPEAKER_00]: Practically speaking, the current
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Extinguishing of that...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not extinguishing of this particular conceiving, of that particular problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's extinguishing of you being here and now.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if here and now, as a most fundamental general context, is experienced, what would then be the extinguishing of it, without, sort of, destroying it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, obviously, destruction of here and now is not nibbāna either.
[SPEAKER_01]: What are the assumptions about experience?
[SPEAKER_01]: Such as?
[SPEAKER_01]: Assumptions that I'm in control of things, that things are for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well... Where are those assumptions?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that something you can see directly?
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously not, because if you see directly, then you will see immediately it's not yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, extinguishing of those assumptions, what does that entail?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you can extinguish the assumption of I am, and still not be in nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means extinguishing I am contains something that pertains to nibbāna, but it's not sufficient in itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like abandoning attavāda does not take you to nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Still, there's this kind of sense of control.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but what is it that's in common to all those assumptions that you want to extinguish?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the more fundamental thing that's present in them, that you do extinguish through extinguishing assumptions, that then, basically, eh... establishes experience of nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Greed, aversion and delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Always.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, can you have sense of self,
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you have a sense of control?
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you have any form of other implicit desire?
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, the extinguishing of being, it's not the extinguishing of here and now that it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's extinguishing of greed, aversion, delusion within here and now.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's when nibbāna becomes visible here and now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not because he was elsewhere.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you brought it into here and now as a special experience that, sort of, you haven't understood at the time, but it was so overwhelming, it must have been right, and then you figured it out later.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's mysticism.
[SPEAKER_00]: You brought it here and now because it was always here and now.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was being obscured.
[SPEAKER_00]: You remove the obscurities, that's how you get to experience it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a good revert to, like, nibbāna, dhāt, the element of nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means the possibility of nibbāna is always here and now because the possibility of abandoning greed, aversion, delusion
[SPEAKER_00]: So, can you find greed, aversion, delusion, anywhere else, anywhere else, apart from your feeling?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Impossible, because...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, understanding the context of the feeling, then, understanding the nature of the feeling... Removes the assumptions about the feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Removes the basis for any desire towards the feeling, which then stops feeding the assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not like you choose to remove this assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: You, you...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's indirect in a sense of you discern what the basis for assumption is, which is lacking the knowledge of the nature of the presently enduring feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by developing that basis, or rather by removing the basis, which is lacking of the knowledge, so by replacing the basis of lacking with the knowledge, lacking of the knowledge, replacing it with the knowledge, you have removed the basis for for assumptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's how assumptions will cease.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why nibbāna is determined in that indirect sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's determined upon your effort to enter nibbāna, your effort to develop nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why, again, that's why I say nibbāna is not a special non-experience or in-between experience and non-experience that kind of overrides everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nibbāna is also one of the dhammas.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, everything, every context you're in, it's a form of dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a form of phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's where your mind is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And nibbāna is also so.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only difference between nibbāna dhamma and any other non-nibbāna dhamma is whether it's determined by greed, aversion, delusion, whether it's determined by the wrong order, whether it's determined by the lacking of the understanding of feeling, whether it's determined by any approach that you find in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, also, Arahantakṣu, if he would know exactly
[SPEAKER_01]: What would make him angry, but he doesn't get angry, in some way.
[SPEAKER_00]: He could know exactly what used to make him angry.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: What used to make him last for, what used to make him distracted.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just remember there was one incident, I think, with Arjun Chah, and they asked him if he still gets angry.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the way he said, apparently, was something like, yes, but I don't pick it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the sense, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe he meant, I recognize what can annoy me, what maybe would be angry, but... Yeah, I don't know what he meant.
[SPEAKER_00]: He could have meant anything by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But yeah, yeah, he could mean there is a degree of disagreeable, but I'm not picking it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it can also mean, oh, I choose to not pick it up, which means you, you are affected by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, it's a good thing that you don't pick it up, but that's not enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: You also want to not be affected by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The same with desire, probably, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, also, you can see, even the Buddha recognized what's a beautiful thing there in the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that doesn't look like... doesn't affect anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because he... this is just fundamental things.
[SPEAKER_01]: He sees that he...
[SPEAKER_01]: Feeling is feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why does... why does the Buddha doesn't have... why does he doesn't... why does he lack desire towards beautiful things?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is there no desire towards beautiful things?
[SPEAKER_01]: Just general recognizing that he doesn't have control, because his eyes exactly trying to control your feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well... Feelings in its own nature rising and ceasing, while the patujanas try to
[SPEAKER_00]: I think people can recognize that they can have control and then have desire in regard to not having control.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anything can be taken by desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, some people find the thrill, find the desire in not having control, in submitting their control.
[SPEAKER_00]: They find pleasurable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if they were containing the desire, then those people would not be able to experience desire on account of non-control.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, they do.
[SPEAKER_00]: But why doesn't the Buddha experience desire towards beautiful things in the world?
[SPEAKER_01]: Dhamma disappears.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because dhamma is painful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dhamma is painful?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, again, if that's all it takes, there would be no dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: If dhamma is painful, you'll automatically be free from dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the whole purpose of Buddhism is to avoid pain, and not want to pain, and not give in to pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it can't be that either.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why does the Buddha have no desire towards beautiful things in the world?
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know how to answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, I just... this kind of assumption disappears and... Well, all of those are kind of theoretical answers.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well...
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't answer it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Assumption disappears.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why does the assumption disappear?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is there no desire towards beautiful things in the world?
[SPEAKER_00]: For a mind that's fully awakened?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or for a mind that's beyond sensuality?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that assumption about me and the world disappears and...
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, yeah, it does.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why does that assumption disappear?
[SPEAKER_01]: I guess, again, a little bit theoretical answer, because the ignorance disappears.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why does the ignorance disappear?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because knowledge arises.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's a good... knowledge arises.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why does the knowledge arise?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, also, all it is like, there's no, like, wrong answer, but there is not accurate enough answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's dig more into it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why does the knowledge arise in regard to beautiful things, so there is no desire?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the knowledge in regard to beautiful things, so there is no desire towards them?
[SPEAKER_01]: I do have answers.
[SPEAKER_01]: It keeps coming up, but I know that wouldn't be the right answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I think I'm good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Care to tell me?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no, it kind of defeats the purpose.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Give some other answer that comes to mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter even if it's not accurate enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, understanding the whole nature as a whole, when it's also understanding the actually
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing really stands on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: The things are already determined.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's already kind of given beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: That actually you didn't have really control over those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: But all of that is kind of secondary psychologizing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like providing reasons to yourself why you shouldn't do it like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why you should not have desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, it's because of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's because of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: None of that is simultaneously seen as an underlying cause because of which you will be unable to experience desire towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is, let me put it like this, what is simultaneously present in every experience of beautiful, on account of which you can experience non-desire?
[SPEAKER_01]: Feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: We can't reach the second question.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, let's let's let's do it again.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like experience of beautiful, like beautiful sight.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there is a desire towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the starting point.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't approve that desire by providing explanations why that's not right or why that's not beautiful or why this or why that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's you trying to manage your desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mysterious world.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, direct insight requires you to see
[SPEAKER_00]: Through that which is beautiful, towards which you have desire, so as a result of that direct seeing, there is no desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not as a result of your effort to cover up desire, or to manage it, or to explain it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you become unable to have desire towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what knowledge of beautiful means.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I'm asking you, what is that knowledge of beautiful, that will result in you being unable to have desire, in the same sense as the Buddha said, you would be unable to have desire towards the food you just vomited.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, just because you see it's not so pleasant as you thought it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see it is not so pleasant as you thought it is?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not pleasant, because you see it's either... What is not pleasant?
[SPEAKER_01]: Dukkha within it.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the dukkha?
[SPEAKER_01]: Dukkha is...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, what is the dukkha in that particular case?
[SPEAKER_00]: Not general, but dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: The determination is dukkha, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is the determination of beautiful?
[SPEAKER_00]: That is dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: The eye?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, that's not determination of beautiful.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Lust?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the result of an ignorance, of not knowing determination.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is the determination of beautiful?
[SPEAKER_00]: That when not known, you have desire towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: When known, you don't have desire towards it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Feeling?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, in regard to beautiful, not in regard to feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, there is material shapes, perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: Perception?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but what kind of perception?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because beautiful is a perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what?
[SPEAKER_00]: Determination of beautiful is beautiful?
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't think about it theoretically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Think about it through the experience of something beautiful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Recollect something beautiful that you had desire towards.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, obviously, you don't act towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, sensory strain is there, established beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, now, in the experience of beautiful that you have desire towards, you want to see what is that determination.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you were right.
[SPEAKER_00]: On account of which, you will be unable to maintain that desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like, oh, I'll see this, and then I'll say no to my desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not accurate enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is beautiful in the experience is, like, normal language would say, like, past experiences we have about the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, okay, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Take a memory, take whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, so, it's a memory of a beautiful experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'm not asking you what is beautiful in that.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm asking you what is determining that beautiful.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is a necessary base for that?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is a saṅkhara of that beautiful?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you brought it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, obviously, arahant recognizes what is beautiful, so I can't say it's ignorance or something else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Beautiful is beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: So... That's why I asked, why does the Buddha does not... why doesn't an arahant... Just see the beautiful, but nothing more.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no desire towards beautiful.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, because he always needs to explain to himself why this is not worth desiring in.
[SPEAKER_00]: He just simply has no desire towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same sense, you don't need to explain to yourself why you shouldn't eat your vomit.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just won't, because it's disgusting.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what's in every heart of beautiful?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's in heart of every experience of beautiful?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is that, the determination?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's... Well, yeah, see.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Desire for more of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's only the response to being misperceived as beautiful.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is beforehand?
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean... What is... not beforehand in the sense of what was before it became beautiful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's... What is it...
[SPEAKER_00]: Context.
[SPEAKER_00]: As you said, what is the determination of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: That if you can see correctly, you will not have desire towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Think of it... okay, let's take that simile from the Sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's take that simile from the Sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, not quite.
[SPEAKER_00]: The beautiful, tasty beverage.
[SPEAKER_00]: Perfect in taste, color, smell, beautiful drink in every regard.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's poison there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't know there's poison there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're fully gripped by the desire to consume that drink.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're fully there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's beautiful and there's desire towards that beautiful, towards consumption, towards engaging with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then you find out there is a poison in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the drink hasn't changed.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your perception of it hasn't changed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's still the same smell, taste, touch, same consistency.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now you have no desire towards it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because now you know it's a poison.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what's the poison in other contexts?
[SPEAKER_01]: You see, it's a kind of danger, you see, in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, now the same thing,
[SPEAKER_00]: Through the heart of the same drink, still in front of you, you can still smell it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see that it's dangerous if you engage with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's sufficient for you to not have desire towards it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's the danger that will prevent you from having desire towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But not danger in a sense you've been doing, like explaining the danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, or, or, or, or, psychologizing the danger and saying, because this is not in my control, because of this, because of this, because of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: All that's true theoretically, but none of that can serve the basis for you uprooting the desire, because that danger needs to be seen through that thing that is beautiful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not in response to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not after, or before, or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you see the heart of every beautiful to be dangerous, you cannot possibly want it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would be inconceivable to have desire towards it, regardless the extent of the beauty, heavenly beauty, like the factually, absolutely, like the most refined beauty you can imagine.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's equally dangerous.
[SPEAKER_00]: It still shares the same nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why the mind who is fully awakened will not have any desire, not just towards this worldly things, but even, you know, the ideas of heavens or even experiences or whatever, devas and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just cannot be wanted, because any form of beauty is dangerous in that sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is it dangerous?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the danger?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, first things, I would say that
[SPEAKER_00]: So, again, keep the same principle in mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Beautiful?
[SPEAKER_00]: Within beautiful, you see dangerous.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, further, within beautiful, that it's dangerous, what else do you see as characteristics of that same thing that's presently enduring?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because more you're... because... if somebody sees through these things, it's dangerous, and then keep gratifying that object.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just like... you're also gratifying the whole...
[SPEAKER_01]: Assumption about the beautiful thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you're not aware of any of those things when you're engaging in gratification, so none of that can play the part.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what is there apparent in that danger?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or what is there that can be apparent in that danger?
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, what are the characteristics of danger?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is danger dangerous?
[SPEAKER_01]: Dangerous because you may be... you're allowing yourself... No.
[SPEAKER_00]: As soon as you started with maybe,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not going to be an accurate answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because now you're trying to figure it out, not trying to describe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Take the experience of danger, any danger, and look for what is the nature of being exposed to danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have no control.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have no control.
[SPEAKER_00]: You start losing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're slaved.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, say again?
[SPEAKER_00]: Slaved.
[SPEAKER_00]: Enslaved.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: I thought you said something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, danger implies non-control.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, you ask yourself further.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is non-control always unpleasant?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what other things are there that are always present in danger?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, take that non-control further.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is that non-control dangerous?
[SPEAKER_01]: Gratification is still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is... Don't think about gratification now.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm asking you, why is danger dangerous?
[SPEAKER_00]: You say, because it's not... it has no control.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why is the non-control dangerous?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the difference between non-dangerous non-control and dangerous non-control?
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, what's the difference between danger and non-danger?
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, when dangerous becomes... when it goes against your own desire and preferences, your own expectations...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, true, but not accurate enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not accurate enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, imagine you're under... you're exposed to some danger now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is that danger?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the nature of danger?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the definition of it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Painful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is it painful?
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, I would say the same things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Losing control.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, but then I'm just revolving around...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why is not having control?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a characteristic.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pain?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do danger?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a characteristic, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do these things have in common?
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Say whatever comes to mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, non-accurate answer is not a wrong answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by providing a non-accurate answer, you define what's more accurate than that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what's in common to danger, non-control and unpleasantness of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the common characteristic?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the unifying characteristic that makes danger dangerous?
[SPEAKER_00]: That makes danger unpleasant?
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe the... not able to face is impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is not permanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no sense of... there's no permanence in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Security is safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: Safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is the characteristic, then, of non-safety?
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't feel safe.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, lack of safety defines what's dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if things are safe, they're automatically not dangerous.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you don't think about safety, any experience of danger means it's a threat.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means you are subjected to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And yes, it means you have no control in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means that threat is already unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if that danger is far removed, not like acute, immediate, the fact that it brings the glimpse of, ultimately, you are under threat.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your life is under threat.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your life can end.
[SPEAKER_00]: Things that you hold to be yours can be swept away.
[SPEAKER_00]: The recognition of the whole thing, that's why it's dangerous.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, those are the characteristics you want to see
[SPEAKER_00]: In beautiful objects in the world, like safety, threat, danger, non-control, directly while they're present, not in response to them as a management technique.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's, I mean, you need, like, people need to learn how to allow things to endure and then see through them what else is simultaneously they're enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, you wouldn't be talking about characteristics of danger when danger is gone, because then it becomes an extra thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You discern the danger and then you can discern the simultaneous characteristics that define that danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why is then lack of safety?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is that unpleasant and unwanted?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do you prefer sense of safety and a kind of non-safety?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, like, you know, the whole assumption I am is going to be feeling of dying and... and you want to protect it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you don't even know.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you don't think those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'm asking you things that you do think.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is, why do you value safety?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is safety more desirable than non-safety?
[SPEAKER_00]: Pleasant, comfortable.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's pleasant and comfortable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why is then the pleasure more wanted and this pleasure not wanted?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because pleasure gives you more assumed
[SPEAKER_01]: Confirmation that there is safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the result of you wanting that pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why do you want pleasure and not want pain?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do you act towards protecting your pleasure and act towards avoiding pain?
[SPEAKER_01]: Just because it's painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no reason why you prefer pleasure on account of pain, and that's why you automatically do so.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't know that there is no reason, and that's how... that becomes your reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you suddenly rec... or, not suddenly, if you make the effort to go
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just choose to act like that, for a gratuitous assumption, because that's what you wanted.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why it's possible to undo it.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, if the reason for your craving towards feeling of pleasure, or towards feeling of pain, or towards neutral feeling, would be rooted in feeling or something other, you wouldn't be able to uproot it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not rooted in anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's always a gratuitous response in regard to what you're presently feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ignorance is utterly completely beginningless.
[SPEAKER_00]: Craving is completely beginningless.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's not in the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not the result of aggregates moving and coming together or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just experience of aggregates means you crave the world against or kind of away from them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there is no reason for that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And until you find out that there is no reason for that, that will be your reason for maintaining that craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're free from craving, you cannot possibly be acting towards
[SPEAKER_00]: On account of how you're feeling, if you don't act on account of how you're feeling, you cannot possibly be exposing yourself to threat of danger, non-danger, safety, non-safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're not exposing to the threat of that, means you have no desire towards things that are kind of offering you safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you don't value safety anymore, because you realize it wasn't safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sensuality and pleasure is the safety for unenlightened mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_00]: Putujana, when touched by unpleasant feeling, doesn't know any other way of dealing, of overcoming, of not being affected by that discomfort, except trying to go into sensual desire and response, cover it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the only form of safety he knows.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, for as long as you don't question that form of safety and see it as non-safe, inherently dangerous, you will always regard it, have a view that it's safe, that it's desirable, that it's wanted, that it should be obtained.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if in the heart of that safety, you suddenly realize, oh my goodness, this is a trap.
[SPEAKER_00]: See?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, there's a safe space for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Come in, come in.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I can sort of trap you in and kill you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if that danger becomes apparent in that safety, you realize this is not safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you would not have to... you wouldn't need to then explain to yourself why you shouldn't have desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Automatically, you will not have desire anymore because it's dangerous.